<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><root>
	<book id="PHM">
			<c id="1">
				<v id="1" bcv="PHM.1.1">Paul, a prisoner of Christ Jesus, and Timothy our brother, to Philemon, our beloved fellow worker,</v>
				<v id="2" bcv="PHM.1.2">to the beloved Apphia, to Archippus our fellow soldier, and to the assembly in your house:</v>
				<v id="3" bcv="PHM.1.3">Grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.</v>
				<v id="4" bcv="PHM.1.4">I thank my God always, making mention of you in my prayers,</v>
				<v id="5" bcv="PHM.1.5">hearing of your love and of the faith which you have toward the Lord Jesus, and toward all the saints,</v>
				<v id="6" bcv="PHM.1.6">that the fellowship of your faith may become effective in the knowledge of every good thing which is in us in Christ Jesus.</v>
				<v id="7" bcv="PHM.1.7">For we have much joy and comfort in your love, because the hearts of the saints have been refreshed through you, brother.</v>
				<v id="8" bcv="PHM.1.8">Therefore though I have all boldness in Christ to command you that which is appropriate,</v>
				<v id="9" bcv="PHM.1.9">yet for love’s sake I rather beg, being such a one as Paul, the aged, but also a prisoner of Jesus Christ.</v>
				<v id="10" bcv="PHM.1.10">I beg you for my child, whom I have become the father of in my chains, Onesimus,
				</v>
				<v id="11" bcv="PHM.1.11">who once was useless to you, but now is useful to you and to me.</v>
				<v id="12" bcv="PHM.1.12">I am sending him back. Therefore receive him, that is, my own heart,</v>
				<v id="13" bcv="PHM.1.13">whom I desired to keep with me, that on your behalf he might serve me in my chains for the Good News.</v>
				<v id="14" bcv="PHM.1.14">But I was willing to do nothing without your consent, that your goodness would not be as of necessity, but of free will.</v>
				<v id="15" bcv="PHM.1.15">For perhaps he was therefore separated from you for a while, that you would have him forever,</v>
				<v id="16" bcv="PHM.1.16">no longer as a slave, but more than a slave, a beloved brother, especially to me, but how much rather to you, both in the flesh and in the Lord.</v>
				<v id="17" bcv="PHM.1.17">If then you count me a partner, receive him as you would receive me.</v>
				<v id="18" bcv="PHM.1.18">But if he has wronged you at all or owes you anything, put that to my account.</v>
				<v id="19" bcv="PHM.1.19">I, Paul, write this with my own hand: I will repay it (not to mention to you that you owe to me even your own self besides).</v>
				<v id="20" bcv="PHM.1.20">Yes, brother, let me have joy from you in the Lord. Refresh my heart in the Lord.</v>
				<v id="21" bcv="PHM.1.21">Having confidence in your obedience, I write to you, knowing that you will do even beyond what I say.</v>
				<v id="22" bcv="PHM.1.22">Also, prepare a guest room for me, for I hope that through your prayers I will be restored to you.</v>
				<v id="23" bcv="PHM.1.23">Epaphras, my fellow prisoner in Christ Jesus, greets you,</v>
				<v id="24" bcv="PHM.1.24">as do Mark, Aristarchus, Demas, and Luke, my fellow workers.</v>
				<v id="25" bcv="PHM.1.25">The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with your spirit. Amen.</v>
			</c>
		</book>
</root>